Over the course of my Instagram career,
I've gotten more than two billion views.
And in today's episode, I'm going to
share with you the seven key lessons
that I've learned about human psychology
along the way. And I'm sure that a more
attention-grabbing title for this video
would have been the seven things that I
learned about the algorithm along the
way. But in all reality, that's kind of
tip number zero, which is that the focus
should be on the audience, not the
algorithm. If you can understand human
psychology and even to take it a step
further, understand the psychology of
your ICP, your ideal customer profile,
then you'll win. You'll get views. You
won't constantly be playing catch-up
trying to figure out what hooks are
trending, what formats are going viral,
and what audios are people using to blow
up their Instagram right now. Instead,
you'll be able to consistently get
views, engagement, and grow your
following. Yes, you need a basic
understanding of how the algorithm
works, but if you can truly understand
human psychology, then you will win on
social media. Fortunately, the algorithm
is designed for humans. And so, even
though the algorithm changes every day,
it's ultimately constantly changing and
evolving and adapting to meet the needs
and the demands and the desires that us
humans, the actual consumers are
expressing. It is changing and being
tweaked to match the triggers and the
signals that we are giving it. And that
leads me directly into the first lesson
learned, which is that people share
posts to say something about themselves,
not necessarily because of the post
itself, and rarely because of the person
who created the post. First of all, I've
talked about this many times before, but
shares are the number one metric for
growth, views, and virality on
Instagram. And next week, I'm going to
be doing an entire episode talking more
in depth about how to get shares. So,
make sure you hit the subscribe button
to stay tuned for that. But in general,
from a human psychology standpoint, when
people share something, they do so
because they're trying to signal or say
something about themselves. Let's say I
see your post and I think it's super
funny and so I send it to my wife Tay. I
am sharing it with her to signal to her
that I am funny or that I am the source
of the funny material. Yes, ultimately
you are the creator. You are the person
who posted the funny meme, but I'm
sharing it to say something about
myself. And so the challenge for you is
to really understand and empathize with
your ideal followers so that you can
know what it is that they want to say
about themselves. What are their
self-beliefs both positively and
negatively? What are they trying to
signal to their friends and families and
the people who follow them? Basically,
when people share your post, it's a way
for them to signal their identity to
others. And when I started thinking more
about this myself and thinking more
about my ideal target followers and
customers, I realized that they're
almost all small business owners. And
universally across the board, small
business owners struggle with lack of
support from friends and family. When
you're first getting started as a solo
entrepreneur, building your personal
brand or your business, it feels like,
"Oh my gosh, I just can't get the
support. My friends and family aren't
hyping me up. I can't grow my
following." And it just feels like
you're yelling into the void. And so I
began creating content that kind of
signaled this or called this out or
sometimes explicitly stated that, you
know, my friends don't support me as
much as the strangers do or it costs
nothing to share and support someone on
Instagram. And as I started creating
messages like that, the small business
owners and soloreneurs and personal
brands who followed me on Instagram
began sharing my posts and those posts
specifically so much more. When you
truly empathize with your ICP and you
understand their psychology, you're also
able to eventually, the highest level of
this is to tap into the things that they
want to say, but that they'll never say
out loud. The things that they believe
or the things that they wish other
people knew, but they're too shy or
timid or scared or nervous to say it
themselves. And so, when you post saying
those things, they can then share your
post to amplify your voice. And it's
kind of like a way that they can say it
without directly saying it. And by far
the best way to understand the
psychology of your ICP is to have direct
conversations with them. Whether that's
in the comment section, in the direct
messages, having consultation calls,
hosting free one-on-one coaching. That's
something that I did a ton of when I was
first getting started growing on
Instagram. And it's still something that
I do to this day. I'm constantly giving
away free 15minute coaching calls as
rewards, as prizes, and giveaways on my
Instagram because, yes, it's a great
incentive for engagement, but for me
personally, I get so much out of those
15-minute one-on-one sessions because
I'm having real conversations with real
human beings, and I'm getting to hear
their concerns, their fears, the things
that they're struggling with, and I'm
able to hear the words that they're
willing to tell me in a private
one-on-one call, but they would never
post about on Instagram. And so then I
can turn those sentiments, I can turn
those ideas, I can turn those identities
into posts that they will then be so
much more likely to share. The second
absolute fact that I've learned about
human psychology as I've gotten more
than two billion views on Instagram is
that nobody is watching. And I know that
that sounds silly because I got two
billion views and yet what I have
learned is true that nobody's watching
or maybe more precisely nobody's paying
attention. People are watching, they're
scrolling, but no one's paying
attention. And while I think there's
definitely a negative side to the fact
that there is no one paying attention,
and while it can definitely be hard to
get in front of people nowadays, and
while the human attention span is
shorter than a goldfish, that's a fact.
You can look it up. I think there's
actually four key benefits that I choose
to focus on when I'm considering the
fact that nobody's paying attention.
Number one, it gives me permission to
post more. It is true on Instagram that
the more you post, the more you grow.
And oftentimes when I say that, one of
the chief concerns that comes to
people's mind is overwhelming their
followers or spamming their feed so that
their followers are like, "Oh my god,
I'm overwhelmed. It's too much." I am
someone who posts five times a day on
Instagram. And yet, I know that the vast
majority of my almost 1 million
followers will not see most of my posts.
And if they do see any of my posts,
they're probably not paying that close
of attention. And so if they see another
post that's literally covering the exact
same topic or telling the exact same
story or even another post later that
afternoon after they saw one of my posts
in the morning, they're probably not
even going to notice and they're
probably not going to care because
they're not paying that much attention.
And so that gives me permission to post
more and thus grow more and not concern
with overwhelming or spamming people.
The second benefit to no one paying
attention is that you can literally post
the same thing multiple times. And this
is one of the strategies that I
recommend. It's called upycling. And
it's basically taking a post that you
have already posted and once 90 days
have passed, literally posting it again.
Same exact post, same exact caption,
same audio, literally same everything,
just re-uploading it. You don't need to
delete or archive or do anything to the
original. You don't need to announce
that it's a repost because again, no one
is paying attention. And so very few
people saw it the first time. And the
very few who did see it, they don't
remember seeing it because they weren't
paying that much attention. But
additionally, besides just directly
upycling and reposting something from
the past, you can constantly be sharing
the same tips, telling the same stories,
giving the same ideas, teaching the same
lessons over and over again. Because
ultimately, for most people, it's going
in one ear and out the other. Meet
Brevo, the all-in-one marketing and CRM
platform that is designed to help you
connect with your customers, boost
engagement, and grow your business
smarter. With Brevo, you can manage all
of your customer interactions in one
place, nurture leads with their built-in
CRM, reach your audience through both
email and SMS, and keep your audience
coming back with powerful automations.
But here's where it gets really
exciting. Meet Aura, Brevo's AI
assistant. Aura helps you craft smarter
campaigns by recommending personalized
suggestions, optimizing send times, and
even analyzing performance data to
improve your strategy in real time. It's
like having a marketing expert on your
team 24/7. And of course, Brevo offers
advanced analytics, streamless
integrations, and AIdriven
personalization. Everything that you
need to create multi-channel campaigns
that hit the mark every time. Get
started for free today or use code tribe
50 to save 50% on starter and standard
plans for the first 3 months of the
annual subscription. Just head to
www.brevo.com/tribe
to take your marketing further with
Brevo and Aura. The third one I hope is
going to provide a huge piece of
permission and a huge sense of relief
for you. And that's that since no one is
paying attention, no one is noticing
your mistakes. They don't care. In
reality, the only person who is noticing
the imperfections, the cluttered
background, the typo, the misspelled
word, the food that was in your teeth,
the hair that was out of place, the
smudge of in your makeup. No one is
noticing that besides you. We are all
our own harshest critics. And that's one
of the reasons that no one's paying
attention is because everyone is so
self-absorbed. Everyone is so busy
paying attention to their own problems
and their own flaws and their own
mistakes and their own challenges and
their own futures and their own
anxieties and their own past and their
own traumas and all that. They're way
too busy worried about their dang selves
to worry about you. And so that gives
you permission, I hope, to make
mistakes, to experiment, to try new
things, to flop. I hear often times the
business owners are scared to flop. And
I believe that if you're not flopping on
Instagram, you're not going to be
growing. I believe that at least 20% of
your posts should be a flop. They should
be a failure. They should be a post that
isn't getting very many views because
the purpose of every post should not be
to go viral. You need to have a good
amount of experimentation. You need to
have a good amount of trial and error.
And part of trial and error is error.
Part of failing until you learn is
failing. And fortunately, because no
one's paying attention, you have
permission. You have permission to
change niches. You have permission to
try new styles of content. You have
permission to test out new theories and
new uh kinds of reels. You have
permission to try out new trends. You
have permission to make those mistakes
because no one cares and no one is
paying attention. And the fourth thing
that's really awesome about no one
paying attention is that you don't have
to be like a college professor. You
don't have to be like the world's
leading expert or be super smart in any
given field or to be like the world's
leading expert in your domain in order
to grow on Instagram. In fact, one of my
favorite formats that is currently super
popular is explaining different
nutrition topics or fitness topics as if
I have CTE. This format was created by
Josh Gilliam. And while it's silly and
while it's a little bit over the top and
his oversimplification of the way he's
speaking, it is kind of a play on the
modern lack of attention and the modern
uh ability to focus and learn on social
media, the modern literacy rates as low
as they are. And so you have permission
to dumb it down, to simplify your reels,
to use easier to understand language.
You don't need to impress people by
using fancy vocab and big words and
trying to teach these big topics and
terms when often times that's going to
be less effective because people are
going to zone out. It's going to go over
their head. They're going to stop paying
attention. So dumb it down. Simplify
your teaching which makes it easier for
you as an educator if you are an
educational entrepreneur. And then that
allows also your audience to pay more
attention and actually learn more in the
process. So keep it simple, sweetie.
That should be easier on you and it will
be easier on your audience as well. The
third thing that I've learned about
human psychology is that everyone can
smell your BS. And I don't know
scientifically why this happens, but we
all can tell. And I think that over the
last 5 years, I think that since 2020,
our BS radar has been finely tuned. Our
nose is really dialed in to be able to
smell that stuff from a mile away. We
can smell when someone is pandering to
get engagement. We can smell when
someone is about to start selling to us.
We can smell and detect when someone is
using AI in their content. And so the
biggest recommendation that I have for
you is to stop trying to trick your
audience. And often times tricking your
audience is because you're trying to
cater to or pander to the algorithm.
Stop doing that. That sort of stuff
might have worked in 2014, 2015, but
it's 2026. We're almost in 2027 now.
Stop trying the BS hacks and tricks
because people can smell that stuff from
a mile away. Instead, make sure that you
have a good heart. Make sure that your
intentions are in the right places, that
you're truly trying to serve rather than
sell and you're about the transformation
more than the transaction. And finally,
if you aren't excited about what you're
posting, if you aren't excited about
what you're doing, if you don't love
what it is that you are sharing online,
that's going to come through in your
content. If you're just kind of mailing
it in and throwing spaghetti against the
wall and posting things because you
heard from some guy on some podcast who
has a buzz cut and a beard that you have
to post a certain amount of times per
day. I'm talking about myself that you
have to post certain amount of times and
so you're like, "Oh, I guess I just got
to post it today. I just got to throw
something against the wall and you're
just kind of halfassing it and mailing
it in." Of course, that's not going to
work. Like people can smell that. And
again, I don't know if it's because
we've all been on social media for 15,
20 years now. I don't know if it's
because the modern consumer is consuming
tens of thousands of videos a day and so
they just get really really good at
spotting what they like and what they
don't like, what is real and what is
fake, but I mean ultimately if you
aren't excited about what you're
posting, if you're not enjoying the
process, I'm not saying that you need to
love Instagram or you need to love every
step of the way, but if you're not just
enjoying it at a minimum, if you are
mailing it in and you're treating it
like a chore to be posting on social
media, well then that's going to come
through in your content. it's going to
be very tough to grow because of it. The
fourth thing that I've learned about
human psychology is that negativity bias
is real. It's powerful and unfortunately
it's very exploitable. And of course,
negativity bias is basically our brains
hardwiring to pay more attention to the
negative thing than the positive. It's
why that one mean thing that someone
said to you in high school is still in
your head today. It's why that one
negative comment out of the thousands of
positive comments has stuck with you.
And so, I think that there's two things
that you need to keep in mind when it
comes to this negativity bias. Number
one, like I said, it's exploitable. Now,
I don't want you to overdo it. And
actually, studies have shown that if you
overdo the negativity, if you basically
become the negative Nelly and all of
your posts are, don't do this, stop
doing this, the world is ending, drama,
drama, drama, it eventually becomes
white noise. It's one of the reasons
that cable news is so much less engaging
today than it was 10, 15 years ago, is
because they went down the slippery
slope of negativity, negativity,
negativity. Right? If you turn on your
local news, you're going to hear 10
negative stories about car crashes and
murders and whatnot before you hear
about the positive things going on in
your community. But over the course of
decades, that has caused all of us as
consumers to really lose our enjoyment
in the news. When the news first started
posting about all these negative things,
it grabbed our attention. The first ever
car chase that was televised on the news
became a nationally televised event that
millions of people tuned in for. But
now, even likely as I'm speaking right
now, there are probably dozens of car
chases going on around the United States
and around the world, but most of them
you probably won't even hear about
because there's just so much negativity
and the news is filled with so much
negativity that it's lost its luster, if
you will. And so, as a content creator,
I want you to first of all know that
using words like no, that is N O, not K
N O W, but no, stop, don't, avoid, lose,
quit, those sorts of things grab
people's attention. And on average, they
grab people's attention more than their
positive counterparts. It's the reason
that ESPN will use the headline, the
team lost the game, rather than the
other team won the game. Or if they are
talking about the team that won the
game, they won't say the team won the
game. They will say the team snapped
their three-game losing streak. Snapped
and lose. Two negative words. So
whenever you're writing your scripts,
whenever you're coming up with your
hooks, whenever you're deciding what the
content of the post will actually be,
consider, is there a negative angle that
I could take? But just make sure not to
overdo it. Now, I also want to speak to
you as someone who's just a human being,
right? As someone who's a business
owner, as someone who's trying to grow
on Instagram, like I said at the very
beginning of this fourth lesson about
human psychology, it is by far one of
the biggest biases of our Insta Club Hub
members to focus on the negative, to
focus on the unfollows or the post that
didn't get a lot of views or to compare
their own stats to someone else's stats.
And I'm not going to sit here and tell
you that the negatives don't exist or
that you need to not pay attention to
them, but I do think it's important to
number one, remind yourself of the
positives. Number two, to be grateful
for what you have and to literally write
out lists that show what you are
grateful for. And number three, to
remember that social media exists in
kind of two polar opposite extremes that
are super bad for your mental health.
One of which being you are only seeing
other people's wins. You're only seeing
other people's highlight reels, success
stories, and triumphs on social media,
especially on Instagram. And you, for
yourself, are only seeing your own
negative things because of the negative
bias. you're only seeing your own low
views, low engagement, unfollows, lack
of growth. And so that's super
unhealthy. The reality is likely
somewhere a lot more in the middle.
People aren't having as many successes
as they try to portray on Instagram. And
you are having way more successes than
you probably realize if you're just
scrolling and not thinking about it.
Listen, I totally get it. Hiring help
for your business is scary. It's
frustrating. And it is such a headache.
But it shouldn't have to be that way
because Upwork makes it easy to hire
specialized freelancers quickly. You can
browse profiles, review past work, and
get help scoping out the role so you can
hire with confidence and get started
quickly. And with Business Plus, you can
access the top 1% of talent on Upwork
with AI powered shortlisting so you can
get matched with the right freelancer in
less time without having to do endless
searching. Visit upwork.com to post your
job for free. Again, that's upwork.com
to get connected with the top talent
ready to help your business grow. That's
upw.com.
upwork.com. The fifth thing that I've
learned about human psychology is what I
like to call the say, do need gap. And
the say, do need gap is what people say
they need or want is very different from
what they actually take action on. What
they do and that is also very different
from what they actually need. And when
you understand these three things, it's
going to totally change how you post and
how you sell and what you sell. And
here's what I've learned as an example.
By far the number one thing that my
followers say that they want is more
followers. But then when it comes to
what they actually do, they are
constantly chasing viral post ideas.
It's always about viral posts, trending
audios, and things that will make you
get a ton of views. But then neither of
those things are what they need in my
opinion, which are systems, strategies,
and the mindsets necessary to grow their
Instagram. If I were to make a post
about the mindsets you need to grow on
Instagram, no one would watch that
video. But as soon as I make a video
about seven viral real ideas, it blows
up. We did a live training earlier this
year in the Insta Club about the systems
for success. And it was one of our
lowest attended live workshops of the
entire year. Yet, it is also the
workshop that has gotten the most
positive feedback from the people who
did attend it. Because the people who
did attend, they realized that they are
getting what they need and they are
finally able to have success as the
result of watching that recording. But
systems are not sexy and the strategies
and the mindsets that you need are not
necessarily what most people go to when
they're thinking of what they want.
There's also this principle or analogy
that I think about often called the
chocolatecovered carrot. And the
chocolate covered carrot is basically
that most people don't want the carrot.
They don't want the healthy thing, the
thing that's good for them, the thing
that they actually need. They want the
chocolate, the thing that is a quick
fix, the thing that is dopamine, the
thing that is really sweet and that
feels rewarding for a moment. And so as
a business owner, as someone who is
posting on social media, it is your job
to create the chocolatecovered carrot,
the thing that looks very enticing from
the outside and it portrays or comes
across as exactly what people are
looking for, exactly what they say they
want, and exactly what they are going to
choose when they have a bunch of
different options. But then once they
bite into it, yes, they are initially
getting the thing that they came for,
the chocolate, but they're also getting
the thing that they need, the thing
that's going to ultimately help them the
most in the long run, which is the
carrot. The sixth thing that I've
learned about human psychology is that
discipline beats motivation. A question
that I often receive is, "Brock, how do
you stay so motivated?" I've now posted,
at the time of recording this, almost
2,000 straight days on Instagram. How do
you stay so motivated? And the reality
is I don't. There are plenty of days
where I'm not motivated, but I have the
discipline to stick to what I've set out
to do. I have the discipline and I think
not to uh you know toot my own horn but
I think that that was honed over years
and years of being an athlete and being
a college football player like I was I
developed that discipline as a muscle
that I can rely on so that even when I'm
not feeling motivated to make content or
motivated to show up on Instagram, I
still have the discipline to show up
anyways. But the reality is that systems
beat both of those things. systems beat
both discipline and motivation because
there are going to be days where even
the most disciplined person is just
literally not going to be able to create
content. Even the most disciplined
person is going to have life get in the
way. Even the most disciplined person is
going to get married like I did. And I
still posted multiple times on the day
of my wedding. Not because I was
disciplined on that day, but because I
had systems that were already in place
that allowed me to show up to provide
for my audience, to grow my audience, to
serve my followers, and to ultimately
engage with more people and grow my
business as a result because I had
systems that were already in place. Now,
again, as I talked about just a few
minutes ago, systems aren't sexy, but
systems are necessary if you want to get
off the hamster wheel of having to rely
on motivation and/or discipline. And
then the seventh and final thing that
I've learned as I've amassed over two
billion views on Instagram. And this one
has not just been amassed from my own
conclusions from getting views, but also
from going to creator workshops and
going to can lions and meeting all these
other creators who have posted thousands
of times and have millions of followers
is that delusional optimism is required.
This belief that everything will work
out and that everything is figure
outable. That is essentially what is
required if you want to have success on
social. Delusional optimism beats
imposttor syndrome. That's not to say
that you're never going to have doubts.
It's not to say that you're never going
to have imposter syndrome. But that is
to say that more times than not, the
majority of the time, your thought is
this is going to work out. This post is
going to go viral. My ideas are great.
I'm only one post away from success. I
am funny. I am a good storyteller. I am
engaging. I am a good content creator.
This kind of goes back to point number
three about how everyone can smell your
BS in the same way that everyone can
smell if you're a phony, if you're a
fake, if you're just in it for the
money. People can smell it if you truly
believe in yourself. If you truly think
that your posts are funny, if you truly
think that your content is good. And
people want to be around people like
that. No one wants to follow someone or
be in the same room as someone who is a
constant Debbie Downer, who's constantly
doubting themselves, who's constantly
second-guessing everything they're
doing. And so some amount of delusional
optimism, some sort of, you know,
internal belief that just is unshakable
is necessary if you want to really build
a big audience and grow your personal
brand on Instagram. I've even heard it
said that you need a certain amount of
narcissism. And I kind of believe that's
true. I mean, to believe that you are
not only able, but that you are
deserving of having a massive audience
is something that is a little bit
narcissistic. And so I'm not saying that
you need to be a narcissist to grow on
Instagram, but there is some degree of
narcissism required, some degree of I
have a unique story to tell. I have a
unique problem that I have solved. I
have some sort of special gift or talent
or ability that the world needs to see.
And I want to be the person who tells
you that that is true for you. You are
watching this episode and you are
hearing my voice right now because I
believe that there is some story that
you have to tell or some problem that
you have solved or some people out there
that you can truly help. And yes, it
does require some narcissism. does
require some delusional self-belief to
be willing to post about yourself and to
post about the lessons you've learned,
the problems you've solved, whatever it
may be on Instagram in order to find
that audience. So, I hope you believe in
yourself. I believe in you. And as
always, happy networking. [music]
[music]